[MUSIC]
[음악]
In the regression module, we talked about the relationship between error or
회귀 모듈에서는 모델의 오차와 정확도 간의
accuracy in the complexity of the model.
관련성을 알아봤습니다
Let's talk a little bit about the relationship in terms of
이번엔 학습이 필요한 데이터 양을
the amount of data you have to learn.
기준으로 한 관련성을 알아보죠
And we'll explore the question of how much data we need to learn.
어느 정도의 데이터를 배워야 하는지 탐구합니다
And this is a really difficult and complex question in machine learning.
기계학습에서는 어렵고도 복잡한 질문이죠
So of course, the more data you have, the better,
물론 데이터의 질만 괜찮다면
as long as the quality of the data is good.
데이터는 많을수록 좋습니다
And then bad data, lots of bad data, is much worse to having much less,
질나쁜 데이터는 아무리 많아도
much fewer, data points with really good, clean, high-quality data points.
질좋고 깔끔한 소수의 데이터 샘플보다 못합니다
Now there's some theoretical techniques to analyze how much data you need.
필요 데이터 양을 분석하는 이론적인 기법이 있습니다
Many of those help you understand kinda the overall trends, but
전반적인 경향은 알려주지만
really tend to be too loose to use in practice.
실무에서 사용할 정도로 정밀하지 않습니다
In practice, there's some empirical techniques to really try to understand
실무에서는 오차의 크기와 종류를
how much error we're making and what that kind of error looks like.
알아내기 위한 경험적 기법들이 있습니다
And, in the follow-up courses, we're gonna explore those techniques much further, but
이어지는 강의에서 이런 기법들을 자세히 다루지만
let me give you a little bit of guidance and
여기서도 분류에서 어떤 역할을 하는지
a little insight on what that can do within the classification side.
안내와 통찰을 제공하고자 합니다
Now an important representation for this relationship between data and
데이터와 품질 관련성의
quality is what's called the learning curve.
중요한 표현법의 하나는 학습곡선이라 합니다
So a learning curve relates the amount of data that we have for
학습곡선은 훈련 데이터 양과
training with the error that we're making.
오차의 관련성을 나타냅니다
And here we're talking about test error.
테스트 오차를 알아보죠
Now if you have very little data for training,
훈련 데이터가 아주 적다면
then your test error is going to be high.
테스트 오차는 클 것입니다
But if you have a lot of data for training,
훈련 데이터가 많다면
your test error is going to be low.
테스트 오차는 작겠죠
And now, the curve is gonna get better and
데이터를 추가하면 할수록
better as you get more and more and more data.
곡선이 좋아질 겁니다
Whoops, didn't go through that point, so I'm gonna just erase it.
점을 통과하지 않았네요 지우겠습니다
Now here we go.
됐죠
This is an example learning curve where the quality is getting better as we
데이터를 추가할수록 품질이 나아지는
add more data.
학습곡선의 예입니다
Now you may ask, is there a limit?
한계가 있나고요?
Is this quality just going to get better and better forever as you add more data?
데이터를 추가하면 품질이 무한히 좋아지나요?
Now we know that error's going to decrease as we add more data, the test error.
데이터를 추가할수록 오차가 줄어들 겁니다
However, there is some gap here.
하지만 여전히 간극이 있습니다
And the question is whether that gap can go to zero, and the answer's,
이 간극이 0가 될지 보면 답은
in general, no.
일반적으로 아닙니다
This gap is called the bias.
이 간극은 편향이라 불립니다
So let's discuss a little bit what this bias, or this gap, is.
이 편향, 간극이 뭔지 설명하죠
So intuitively,
직관적으로
it says even with infinite data,
데이터가 무한하더라도
the test error will not go to zero.
테스트 오차가 0이 되지는 않습니다
So let's understand why a little bit.
왜인지 잠시 생각해보죠
More complex models tend to have less bias.
복잡한 모델일수록 편향이 적은 경향이 있습니다
So if you look at a sentiment analysis classifier that we may building,
우리가 만들 감성 분석 분류기에서
if you just use single words like awesome,
굉장하다, 좋다, 훌륭하다, 최악이다, 끔찍하다
good, great, terrible, awful, it can do okay.
같이 단어 하나만 사용하면 성능이 그럭저럭 나옵니다
Maybe it do really well, maybe just does okay.
꽤 괜찮을지도 모르지만 대체로 그럭저럭이죠
But even if you have infinite data, even with all the data in the world,
하지만 무한한 데이터, 전세계의 모든 데이터가
you're never gonna get this sentence right, the sushi was not good.
있더라도 초밥은 좋지 않았다는 문장을 제대로 판별하지 못할 것입니다
Because you're not looking at pairs of words,
단어짝을 보지 않기 때문이죠
you're just looking at the words good and not individually.
좋다라는 단어 하나만 봅니다
And so more complex models that, for example, deal with combinations of words,
예를 들어 단어 조합을 고려하는 복잡한 모델은
for example, the simply called the bigram model,
바이그램 모델이라고 하는데
where you look at pairs of secret words like not good.
좋지 않다 같은 연속적인 단어짝을 고려합니다
Those models require more parameters, because there's more possibilities.
이런 모델에는 더 많은 파라미터가 필요한데 가짓수가 많기 때문이죠
They can do better, they may have a parameter for good, say 1.5.
성능도 나은데 좋다에 대한 파라미터는 1.5,
But not good, say -2.1.
좋지 않다는 -2.1를 써서요
And actually get that sentence, the sushi was not good, correctly.
그러면 방금의 문장, 초밥은 좋지 않았다는 제대로 판별하게 됩니다
So they have less bias.
편향이 줄어듭니다
They can represent sentences that couldn't be represented as words, but
단어만으론 표현하지 못했던 문장을 표현해서
so they're potentially more accurate.
더 정확해지는 것이죠
But they need more data to learn, because there's more parameters.
하지만 더 많은 데이터가 필요한데 파라미터가 더 많기 때문입니다
There's not just a parameter for good, there's now a parameter for not good, and
좋다라는 파라미터뿐만 아니라 좋지 않다는 파라미터와
all possible combinations of words.
모든 단어 조합이 있습니다
And the more parameters your model has, in general, the more data you need to learn.
모델에 파라미터가 많을수록 일반적으로 학습 데이터가 더 필요합니다
So let's go back to our example.
다시 예제로 돌아가보죠
We talked about the fact of a amount of training data on the test error.
훈련 데이터의 양이 테스트 오차에 미치는 영향에 대해 알아봤습니다
So let's say that I'm building a classifier using single words.
단어 하나만 가지고 만드는 모델을 설명하죠
And the question is, how does that relate to a classifier, based on pairs of words?
이게 단어짝 기반의 분류기와 연관이 있냐고요?
Now for a classifier based on bigrams, when you have less data,
바이그램 기반 분류기는 데이터가 적을 때
it's not going to do as well because it has more parameters to fit.
성능이 좋지 않은데 더 많은 파라미터를 적합화해야 하기 때문이죠
But when you have more data, it's going to do better because it's going to be able to
하지만 데이터가 많으면 성능이 좋아지는데
capture settings like, the sushi was not good.
초밥은 좋지 않았다 같은 문장을 잡아낼 수 있기 때문이죠
And so the behavior you're gonna get is something like this.
그러므로 예상되는 반응은 다음과 같습니다
And at some point, there's a crossover where it starts doing better than
어느 점에서 바이그램 모델이 유니그램 모델을
the classifier with single words.
성능으로 넘어서게 됩니다
But notice the background model still has some bias here.
하지만 바이그램 모델에도 편향이 있습니다
Although the bias is smaller, it still has some bias.
적기는 하지만 아직 있죠
[MUSIC]
[음악]